<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<chapter id="introduction.installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>
        See the <link linkend="requirements">requirements appendix</link> for a detailed list of
        requirements for Zend Framework.
    </para>

    <para>
        Installing Zend Framework is extremely simple. Once you have downloaded and extracted the
        framework, you should add the <filename>/library</filename> folder in the distribution to
        the beginning of your include path. You may also want to move the library folder
        to another – possibly shared – location on your file system.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/download/latest">Download the latest
                stable release.</ulink> This version, available in both
                <filename>.zip</filename> and <filename>.tar.gz</filename> formats, is a
                good choice for those who are new to Zend Framework.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/download/snapshot">Download the latest
                nightly snapshot.</ulink> For those who would brave the cutting edge, the
                nightly snapshots represent the latest progress of Zend Framework development.
                Snapshots are bundled with documentation either in English only or in all
                available languages. If you anticipate working with the latest Zend Framework
                developments, consider using a Subversion (<acronym>SVN</acronym>) client.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                Using a <ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org">Subversion</ulink>
                (<acronym>SVN</acronym>) client. Zend Framework is open source software, and the
                Subversion repository used for its development is publicly available. Consider
                using <acronym>SVN</acronym> to get Zend Framework if you already use
                <acronym>SVN</acronym> for your application development, want to
                contribute back to the framework, or need to upgrade your framework version
                more often than releases occur.
            </para>

            <para>
                <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.export.html">
                Exporting</ulink> is useful if you want to get a particular framework revision
                without the <filename>.svn</filename> directories as created in a working copy.
            </para>

            <para>
                <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.checkout.html">
                Check out a working copy</ulink> if you want contribute to Zend Framework, a
                working copy can be updated any time with
                <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.update.html">
                svn update</ulink> and changes can be commited to our <acronym>SVN</acronym>
                repository with the
                <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.commit.html">
                svn commit</ulink> command.
            </para>

            <para>
                An
                <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.advanced.externals.html">
                externals definition</ulink> is quite convenient for developers already using
                <acronym>SVN</acronym> to manage their application's working copies.
            </para>

            <para>
                The <acronym>URL</acronym> for the trunk of Zend Framework's <acronym>SVN</acronym>
                repository is: <ulink
                    url="http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/standard/trunk">
                    http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/standard/trunk</ulink>
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        Once you have a copy of Zend Framework available, your application needs to be able to
        access the framework classes. Though there are
        <ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/configuration.changes.php">
        several ways to achieve this</ulink>, your <acronym>PHP</acronym>
        <ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/ini.core.php#ini.include-path">include_path</ulink>
        needs to contain the path to Zend Framework's library.
    </para>

    <para>
        Zend provides a <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/docs/quickstart">QuickStart</ulink>
        to get you up and running as quickly as possible. This is an excellent way to begin
        learning about the framework with an emphasis on real world examples that you can build
        upon.
    </para>

    <para>
        Since Zend Framework components are loosely coupled, you may use a somewhat unique
        combination of them in your own applications. The following chapters provide a
        comprehensive reference to Zend Framework on a component-by-component basis.
    </para>
</chapter>
