<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<chapter id="introduction.overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
        Zend Framework is an open source framework for developing web applications and services
        with <acronym>PHP</acronym> 5. Zend Framework is implemented using 100% object-oriented
        code. The component structure of Zend Framework is somewhat unique; each component is
        designed with few dependencies on other components. This loosely coupled architecture allows
        developers to use components individually. We often call this a "use-at-will" design.
    </para>

    <para>
        While they can be used separately, Zend Framework components in the standard library form a
        powerful and extensible web application framework when combined. Zend Framework offers a
        robust, high performance <acronym>MVC</acronym> implementation, a database abstraction that
        is simple to use, and a forms component that implements <acronym>HTML</acronym> form
        rendering, validation, and filtering so that developers can consolidate all of these
        operations using one easy-to-use, object oriented interface. Other components, such as
        <classname>Zend_Auth</classname> and <classname>Zend_Acl</classname>, provide user
        authentication and authorization against all common credential stores. Still others
        implement client libraries to simply access to the most popular web services available.
        Whatever your application needs are, you're likely to find a Zend Framework component that
        can be used to dramatically reduce development time with a thoroughly tested foundation.
    </para>

    <para>
        The principal sponsor of the project 'Zend Framework' is <ulink url="http://www.zend.com">
        Zend Technologies</ulink>, but many companies have contributed components or significant
        features to the framework. Companies such as Google, Microsoft, and StrikeIron have
        partnered with Zend to provide interfaces to web services and other technologies that they
        wish to make available to Zend Framework developers.
    </para>

    <para>
        Zend Framework could not deliver and support all of these features without the help of the
        vibrant Zend Framework community. Community members, including contributors, make
        themselves available on <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/archives">mailing
            lists</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.zftalk.com">IRC channels</ulink>, and other
        forums. Whatever question you have about Zend Framework, the community is always available
        to address it.
    </para>
</chapter>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
