<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="performance.database"><info><title>Zend_Db Performance</title></info>
    

    <para>
        <classname>Zend_Db</classname> is a database abstraction layer, and is intended to
        provide a common <acronym>API</acronym> for <acronym>SQL</acronym> operations.
        <classname>Zend_Db_Table</classname> is a
        Table Data Gateway, intended to abstract common table-level database
        operations. Due to their abstract nature and the "magic" they do under
        the hood to perform their operations, they can sometimes introduce
        performance overhead.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="performance.database.tableMetadata"><info><title>How can I reduce overhead introduced by Zend_Db_Table for
            retrieving table metadata?</title></info>
        

        <para>
            In order to keep usage as simple as possible, and also to support
            constantly changing schemas during development,
            <classname>Zend_Db_Table</classname> does some magic under the hood: on
            first use, it fetches the table schema and stores it within object
            members. This operation is typically expensive, regardless of the
            database -- which can contribute to bottlenecks in production.
        </para>

        <para>
            Fortunately, there are techniques for improving the situation.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="performance.database.tableMetadata.cache"><info><title>Use the metadata cache</title></info>
            

            <para>
                <classname>Zend_Db_Table</classname> can optionally utilize
                <classname>Zend_Cache</classname> to cache table metadata. This is
                typically faster to access and less expensive than fetching the
                metadata from the database itself.
            </para>

            <para>
                The <link linkend="zend.db.table.metadata.caching"><classname>Zend_Db_Table
                </classname> documentation includes information on metadata caching</link>.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="performance.database.tableMetadata.hardcoding"><info><title>Hardcode your metadata in the table definition</title></info>
            

            <para>
                As of 1.7.0, <classname>Zend_Db_Table</classname> also provides <link linkend="zend.db.table.metadata.caching.hardcoding">support
                for hardcoding metadata in the table definition</link>. This is
                an advanced use case, and should only be used when you know the
                table schema is unlikely to change, or that you're able to keep
                the definitions up-to-date.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="performance.database.select"><info><title>
            SQL generated with Zend_Db_Select s not hitting my indexes; how can I make it better?
        </title></info>
        

        <para>
            <classname>Zend_Db_Select</classname> is relatively good at its job. However,
            if you are performing complex queries requiring joins or
            sub-selects, it can often be fairly naive.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="performance.database.select.writeyourown"><info><title>Write your own tuned SQL</title></info>
            

            <para>
                The only real answer is to write your own <acronym>SQL</acronym>;
                <classname>Zend_Db</classname> does not require the usage of
                <classname>Zend_Db_Select</classname>, so providing your own, tuned
                <acronym>SQL</acronym> select statements is a perfectly legitimate approach,
            </para>

            <para>
                Run <constant>EXPLAIN</constant> on your queries, and test a variety of
                approaches until you can reliably hit your indices in the most
                performant way -- and then hardcode the <acronym>SQL</acronym> as a class property
                or constant.
            </para>

            <para>
                If the <acronym>SQL</acronym> requires variable arguments, provide placeholders in
                the <acronym>SQL</acronym>, and utilize a combination of
                <methodname>vsprintf()</methodname> and <methodname>array_walk()</methodname> to
                inject the values into the <acronym>SQL</acronym>:
            </para>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
// $adapter is the DB adapter. In Zend_Db_Table, retrieve
// it using $this->getAdapter().
$sql = vsprintf(
    self::SELECT_FOO,
    array_walk($values, array($adapter, 'quoteInto'))
);
]]></programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>
