<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="coding-standard"><info><title>Стандарт написання PHP коду в Zend Framework</title></info>
  
    <section xml:id="coding-standard.overview"><info><title>Огляд</title></info>
        

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.overview.scope"><info><title>Сфера застосування</title></info>
            

            <para>
                Цей документ надає вказівки щодо форматування коду та документації для розробників
                та команд які роблять свій вклад в розробку Zend Framework. Багато розробників 
                що використовують Zend Framework також знаходять корисним слідувати 
                цим стандартам щоб писати свій код у відповідності до всього коду Zend Framework.
                Варто зазначити що докладено великих зусиль щоб як найбільш повно описати стандарти кодування.

                <note>
                    <para>
                        Примітка: Sometimes developers consider the establishment of a standard more 
                        important than what that standard actually suggests at the most detailed 
                        level of design. Інколи розробники надають впровадженню стандарту важливішого 
                        значення ніж те, що стандарт дійсно пропонує, на найбільш деталізованому 
                        рівні розробки. Вказівки в стандартах кодування Zend Framework захоплюють 
                        практичні підходи що добре себе зарекомендували в проекті розробки Zend Framework.
                        Дозволяється модифікувати ці стандарти або використовувати їх в незмінному 
                        стані у відповідності до положень нашої 
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://framework.zend.com/license">ліцензії</link>.
                    </para>
                </note>

                Теми що висвітлюються в стандартах кодування Zend Framework включають:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Форматування <acronym>PHP</acronym> файлів</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Принципи іменування</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Стиль написання коду</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Вбудована документація</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.overview.goals"><info><title>Цілі</title></info>
            

            <para>
                Дотримання стандартів написання коду є важливим для будь якого проекту,
                зокрема коли над одним проектом працюють кілька розробників.
                Стандарти написання коду забезпечують високу якість,
                меншу кількість помилок, та легкий супровід коду.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coding-standard.php-file-formatting"><info><title>Форматування PHP файлів</title></info>
        

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.php-file-formatting.general"><info><title>Загальні положення</title></info>
            

            <para>
                Заборонено ставити закриваючий тег ("?&gt;") для файлів що містять виключно 
                <acronym>PHP</acronym> код. Закриваючий тег необов'язковий для <acronym>PHP</acronym>,
                та його відсутність допомагає уникнути випадкового попадання у відповідь сервера 
                пробілу що опинився в кінці файлу.
            </para>

            <note>
                <para>
                <emphasis>Важливо</emphasis>: Включення додаткового бінарного коду як це дозволено при
                використанні <code>__HALT_COMPILER()</code> заборонено для всіх <acronym>PHP</acronym> 
                файлів в проекті Zend framework та похідних файлах. Використання такої можливості 
                дозволено лише для деяких сценаріїв встановлення.
                </para>
            </note>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.php-file-formatting.indentation"><info><title>Відступи</title></info>
            

            <para>Використовувати відступ в 4 пробіли, без табуляції.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.php-file-formatting.max-line-length"><info><title>Максимальна довжина рядка</title></info>
            

            <para>
                Дотримуватися довжини рядка в 80 символів, тобто розробники повинні намагатись тримати 
                код настільки близько до 80-ої колонки наскільки це практично можливо. 
                Проте, довші рядки дозволені. Максимальна довжина будь-якого рядка <acronym>PHP</acronym> коду
                не повинна перевищувати 120 символів.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.php-file-formatting.line-termination"><info><title>Завершення рядків</title></info>
            

            <para>
                Завершення рядка в стандартний спосіб для текстових файлів Unix. Рядки повинні завершуватися 
                через переведення рядка (LF). Переведення рядка представлено десятковим кодом 10,
                та шістнадцятковим 0x0A.
            </para>

            <para>
                Примітка: Не використовувати повернення каретки (CR) у відповідності до ОС Apple (0x0D) або 
                комбінацію повернення каретки - переведення рядка (CRLF) 
                що є стандартом для ОС Windows (0x0D, 0x0A).
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coding-standard.naming-conventions"><info><title>Принципи іменування</title></info>
        

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.classes"><info><title>Класи</title></info>
            

            <para>
                Zend Framework standardizes on a class naming convention whereby the names of the
                classes directly map to the directories in which they are stored. The root level
                directory of Zend Framework's standard library is the "Zend/" directory, whereas
                the root level directory of Zend Framework's extras library is the "ZendX/"
                directory. All Zend Framework classes are stored hierarchically under these root
                directories..
            </para>

            <para>
                Class names may only contain alphanumeric characters. Numbers are permitted
                in class names but are discouraged in most cases. Underscores are only permitted in
                place of the path separator; the filename "<filename>Zend/Db/Table.php</filename>"
                must map to the class name "<classname>Zend_Db_Table</classname>".
            </para>

            <para>
                If a class name is comprised of more than one word, the first letter of each new
                word must be capitalized. Successive capitalized letters are not allowed, e.g.
                a class "Zend_PDF" is not allowed while "<classname>Zend_Pdf</classname>" is
                acceptable.
            </para>

            <para>
                These conventions define a pseudo-namespace mechanism for Zend Framework. Zend
                Framework will adopt the <acronym>PHP</acronym> namespace feature when it becomes
                available and is feasible for our developers to use in their applications.
            </para>

            <para>
                See the class names in the standard and extras libraries for examples of this
                classname convention.
            </para>

            <note>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Important</emphasis>: Code that must be deployed alongside
                    Zend Framework libraries but is not part of the standard or extras libraries
                    (e.g. application code or libraries that are not distributed by Zend) must
                    never start with "Zend_" or "ZendX_".
                </para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.abstracts"><info><title>Abstract Classes</title></info>
            

            <para>
                In general, abstract classes follow the same conventions as <link linkend="coding-standard.naming-conventions.classes">classes</link>,
                with one additional rule: abstract class names must end in the term, "Abstract",
                and that term must not be preceded by an underscore. As an example,
                <classname>Zend_Controller_Plugin_Abstract</classname> is considered an
                invalid name, but <classname>Zend_Controller_PluginAbstract</classname> or
                <classname>Zend_Controller_Plugin_PluginAbstract</classname> would be valid
                names.
            </para>

            <note>
                <para>
                    This naming convention is new with version 1.9.0 of Zend Framework. Classes
                    that pre-date that version may not follow this rule, but will be renamed in
                    the future in order to comply.
                </para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.interfaces"><info><title>Interfaces</title></info>
            

            <para>
                In general, interfaces follow the same conventions as <link linkend="coding-standard.naming-conventions.classes">classes</link>,
                with one additional rule: interface names may optionally end in the term,
                "Interface", but that term must not be preceded by an underscore. As an example,
                <classname>Zend_Controller_Plugin_Interface</classname> is considered an
                invalid name, but <classname>Zend_Controller_PluginInterface</classname> or
                <classname>Zend_Controller_Plugin_PluginInterface</classname> would be valid
                names.
            </para>

            <para>
                While this rule is not required, it is strongly recommended, as it provides a
                good visual cue to developers as to which files contain interfaces rather than
                classes.
            </para>

            <note>
                <para>
                    This naming convention is new with version 1.9.0 of Zend Framework. Classes
                    that pre-date that version may not follow this rule, but will be renamed in
                    the future in order to comply.
                </para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.filenames"><info><title>Filenames</title></info>
            

            <para>
                For all other files, only alphanumeric characters, underscores, and the dash
                character ("-") are permitted. Spaces are strictly prohibited.
            </para>

            <para>
                Any file that contains <acronym>PHP</acronym> code should end with the extension
                "<filename>.php</filename>", with the notable exception of view scripts. The
                following examples show acceptable filenames for Zend Framework classes:
            </para>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
Zend/Db.php

Zend/Controller/Front.php

Zend/View/Helper/FormRadio.php
]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                File names must map to class names as described above.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.functions-and-methods"><info><title>Functions and Methods</title></info>
            

            <para>
                Function names may only contain alphanumeric characters. Underscores are not
                permitted. Numbers are permitted in function names but are discouraged in most
                cases.
            </para>

            <para>
                Function names must always start with a lowercase letter. When a function name
                consists of more than one word, the first letter of each new word must be
                capitalized. This is commonly called "camelCase" formatting.
            </para>

            <para>
                Verbosity is generally encouraged. Function names should be as verbose as is
                practical to fully describe their purpose and behavior.
            </para>

            <para>
                These are examples of acceptable names for functions:
            </para>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
filterInput()

getElementById()

widgetFactory()
]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                For object-oriented programming, accessors for instance or static variables should
                always be prefixed with "get" or "set". In implementing design patterns, such as the
                singleton or factory patterns, the name of the method should contain the pattern
                name where practical to more thoroughly describe behavior.
            </para>

            <para>
                For methods on objects that are declared with the "private" or "protected" modifier,
                the first character of the method name must be an underscore. This is the only
                acceptable application of an underscore in a method name. Methods declared "public"
                should never contain an underscore.
            </para>

            <para>
                Functions in the global scope (a.k.a "floating functions") are permitted but
                discouraged in most cases. Consider wrapping these functions in a static class.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.variables"><info><title>Variables</title></info>
            

            <para>
                Variable names may only contain alphanumeric characters. Underscores are not
                permitted. Numbers are permitted in variable names but are discouraged in most
                cases.
            </para>

            <para>
                For instance variables that are declared with the "private" or "protected" modifier,
                the first character of the variable name must be a single underscore. This is the
                only acceptable application of an underscore in a variable name. Member variables
                declared "public" should never start with an underscore.
            </para>

            <para>
                As with function names (see section 3.3) variable names must always start with a
                lowercase letter and follow the "camelCaps" capitalization convention.
            </para>

            <para>
                Verbosity is generally encouraged. Variables should always be as verbose as
                practical to describe the data that the developer intends to store in them. Terse
                variable names such as "<varname>$i</varname>" and "<varname>$n</varname>" are
                discouraged for all but the smallest loop contexts. If a loop contains more than
                20 lines of code, the index variables should have more descriptive names.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.constants"><info><title>Constants</title></info>
            

            <para>
                Constants may contain both alphanumeric characters and underscores. Numbers are
                permitted in constant names.
            </para>

            <para>
                All letters used in a constant name must be capitalized, while all words in a
                constant name must be separated by underscore characters.
            </para>

            <para>
                For example, <constant>EMBED_SUPPRESS_EMBED_EXCEPTION</constant> is permitted but
                <constant>EMBED_SUPPRESSEMBEDEXCEPTION</constant> is not.
            </para>

            <para>
                Constants must be defined as class members with the "const" modifier. Defining
                constants in the global scope with the "define" function is permitted but strongly
                discouraged.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style"><info><title>Coding Style</title></info>
        

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.php-code-demarcation"><info><title>PHP Code Demarcation</title></info>
            

            <para>
                <acronym>PHP</acronym> code must always be delimited by the full-form, standard
                <acronym>PHP</acronym> tags:
            </para>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
<?php

?>
]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Short tags are never allowed. For files containing only <acronym>PHP</acronym>
                code, the closing tag must always be omitted (See <link linkend="coding-standard.php-file-formatting.general">General standards</link>).
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.strings"><info><title>Strings</title></info>
            

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.strings.literals"><info><title>String Literals</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    When a string is literal (contains no variable substitutions), the apostrophe or
                    "single quote" should always be used to demarcate the string:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$a = 'Example String';
]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.strings.literals-containing-apostrophes"><info><title>String Literals Containing Apostrophes</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    When a literal string itself contains apostrophes, it is permitted to demarcate
                    the string with quotation marks or "double quotes". This is especially useful
                    for <constant>SQL</constant> statements:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$sql = "SELECT `id`, `name` from `people` "
     . "WHERE `name`='Fred' OR `name`='Susan'";
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    This syntax is preferred over escaping apostrophes as it is much easier to read.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.strings.variable-substitution"><info><title>Variable Substitution</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Variable substitution is permitted using either of these forms:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$greeting = "Hello $name, welcome back!";

$greeting = "Hello {$name}, welcome back!";
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    For consistency, this form is not permitted:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$greeting = "Hello ${name}, welcome back!";
]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.strings.string-concatenation"><info><title>String Concatenation</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Strings must be concatenated using the "." operator. A space must always
                    be added before and after the "." operator to improve readability:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$company = 'Zend' . ' ' . 'Technologies';
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    When concatenating strings with the "." operator, it is encouraged to
                    break the statement into multiple lines to improve readability. In these
                    cases, each successive line should be padded with white space such that the
                    "."; operator is aligned under the "=" operator:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$sql = "SELECT `id`, `name` FROM `people` "
     . "WHERE `name` = 'Susan' "
     . "ORDER BY `name` ASC ";
]]></programlisting>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.arrays"><info><title>Arrays</title></info>
            

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.arrays.numerically-indexed"><info><title>Numerically Indexed Arrays</title></info>
                

                <para>Negative numbers are not permitted as indices.</para>

                <para>
                    An indexed array may start with any non-negative number, however
                    all base indices besides 0 are discouraged.
                </para>

                <para>
                    When declaring indexed arrays with the <type>Array</type> function, a trailing
                    space must be added after each comma delimiter to improve readability:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$sampleArray = array(1, 2, 3, 'Zend', 'Studio');
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    It is permitted to declare multi-line indexed arrays using the "array"
                    construct. In this case, each successive line must be padded with spaces such
                    that beginning of each line is aligned:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$sampleArray = array(1, 2, 3, 'Zend', 'Studio',
                     $a, $b, $c,
                     56.44, $d, 500);
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Alternately, the initial array item may begin on the following line. If so,
                    it should be padded at one indentation level greater than the line containing
                    the array declaration, and all successive lines should have the same
                    indentation; the closing paren should be on a line by itself at the same
                    indentation level as the line containing the array declaration:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$sampleArray = array(
    1, 2, 3, 'Zend', 'Studio',
    $a, $b, $c,
    56.44, $d, 500,
);
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    When using this latter declaration, we encourage using a trailing comma for
                    the last item in the array; this minimizes the impact of adding new items on
                    successive lines, and helps to ensure no parse errors occur due to a missing
                    comma.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.arrays.associative"><info><title>Associative Arrays</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    When declaring associative arrays with the <type>Array</type> construct,
                    breaking the statement into multiple lines is encouraged. In this case, each
                    successive line must be padded with white space such that both the keys and the
                    values are aligned:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$sampleArray = array('firstKey'  => 'firstValue',
                     'secondKey' => 'secondValue');
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Alternately, the initial array item may begin on the following line. If so,
                    it should be padded at one indentation level greater than the line containing
                    the array declaration, and all successive lines should have the same
                    indentation; the closing paren should be on a line by itself at the same
                    indentation level as the line containing the array declaration. For
                    readability, the various "=&gt;" assignment operators should be padded such that
                    they align.
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$sampleArray = array(
    'firstKey'  => 'firstValue',
    'secondKey' => 'secondValue',
);
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    When using this latter declaration, we encourage using a trailing comma for
                    the last item in the array; this minimizes the impact of adding new items on
                    successive lines, and helps to ensure no parse errors occur due to a missing
                    comma.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.classes"><info><title>Classes</title></info>
            

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.classes.declaration"><info><title>Class Declaration</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Classes must be named according to Zend Framework's naming conventions.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The brace should always be written on the line underneath the class name.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Every class must have a documentation block that conforms to the PHPDocumentor
                    standard.
                </para>

                <para>
                    All code in a class must be indented with four spaces.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Only one class is permitted in each <acronym>PHP</acronym> file.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Placing additional code in class files is permitted but discouraged.
                    In such files, two blank lines must separate the class from any additional
                    <acronym>PHP</acronym> code in the class file.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The following is an example of an acceptable class declaration:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
/**
 * Documentation Block Here
 */
class SampleClass
{
    // all contents of class
    // must be indented four spaces
}
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Classes that extend other classes or which implement interfaces should
                    declare their dependencies on the same line when possible.
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
class SampleClass extends FooAbstract implements BarInterface
{
}
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    If as a result of such declarations, the line length exceeds the <link linkend="coding-standard.php-file-formatting.max-line-length">maximum line
                        length</link>, break the line before the "extends" and/or "implements"
                    keywords, and pad those lines by one indentation level.
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
class SampleClass
    extends FooAbstract
    implements BarInterface
{
}
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    If the class implements multiple interfaces and the declaration exceeds the
                    maximum line length, break after each comma separating the interfaces, and
                    indent the interface names such that they align.
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
class SampleClass
    implements BarInterface,
               BazInterface
{
}
]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.classes.member-variables"><info><title>Class Member Variables</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Member variables must be named according to Zend Framework's variable naming
                    conventions.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Any variables declared in a class must be listed at the top of the class, above
                    the declaration of any methods.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The <emphasis>var</emphasis> construct is not permitted. Member variables always
                    declare their visibility by using one of the <property>private</property>,
                    <property>protected</property>, or <property>public</property> modifiers. Giving
                    access to member variables directly by declaring them as public is permitted but
                    discouraged in favor of accessor methods (set &amp; get).
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.functions-and-methods"><info><title>Functions and Methods</title></info>
            

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.functions-and-methods.declaration"><info><title>Function and Method Declaration</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Functions must be named according to Zend Framework's function naming
                    conventions.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Methods inside classes must always declare their visibility by using
                    one of the <property>private</property>, <property>protected</property>,
                    or <property>public</property> modifiers.
                </para>

                <para>
                    As with classes, the brace should always be written on the line underneath the
                    function name. Space between the function name and the opening parenthesis for
                    the arguments is not permitted.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Functions in the global scope are strongly discouraged.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The following is an example of an acceptable function declaration in a class:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
/**
 * Documentation Block Here
 */
class Foo
{
    /**
     * Documentation Block Here
     */
    public function bar()
    {
        // all contents of function
        // must be indented four spaces
    }
}
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    In cases where the argument list exceeds the <link linkend="coding-standard.php-file-formatting.max-line-length">maximum line
                        length</link>, you may introduce line breaks. Additional arguments to the
                    function or method must be indented one additional level beyond the function
                    or method declaration. A line break should then occur before the closing
                    argument paren, which should then be placed on the same line as the opening
                    brace of the function or method with one space separating the two, and at the
                    same indentation level as the function or method declaration. The following is
                    an example of one such situation:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
/**
 * Documentation Block Here
 */
class Foo
{
    /**
     * Documentation Block Here
     */
    public function bar($arg1, $arg2, $arg3,
        $arg4, $arg5, $arg6
    ) {
        // all contents of function
        // must be indented four spaces
    }
}
]]></programlisting>

                <note>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Note</emphasis>: Pass-by-reference is the only parameter passing
                        mechanism permitted in a method declaration.
                    </para>
                </note>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
/**
 * Documentation Block Here
 */
class Foo
{
    /**
     * Documentation Block Here
     */
    public function bar(&$baz)
    {}
}
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Call-time pass-by-reference is strictly prohibited.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The return value must not be enclosed in parentheses. This can hinder
                    readability, in additional to breaking code if a method is later changed to
                    return by reference.
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
/**
 * Documentation Block Here
 */
class Foo
{
    /**
     * WRONG
     */
    public function bar()
    {
        return($this->bar);
    }

    /**
     * RIGHT
     */
    public function bar()
    {
        return $this->bar;
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.functions-and-methods.usage"><info><title>Function and Method Usage</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Function arguments should be separated by a single trailing space after the
                    comma delimiter. The following is an example of an acceptable invocation of a
                    function that takes three arguments:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
threeArguments(1, 2, 3);
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Call-time pass-by-reference is strictly prohibited. See the function
                    declarations section for the proper way to pass function arguments by-reference.
                </para>

                <para>
                    In passing arrays as arguments to a function, the function call may include the
                    "array" hint and may be split into multiple lines to improve readability. In
                    such cases, the normal guidelines for writing arrays still apply:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
threeArguments(array(1, 2, 3), 2, 3);

threeArguments(array(1, 2, 3, 'Zend', 'Studio',
                     $a, $b, $c,
                     56.44, $d, 500), 2, 3);

threeArguments(array(
    1, 2, 3, 'Zend', 'Studio',
    $a, $b, $c,
    56.44, $d, 500
), 2, 3);
]]></programlisting>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.control-statements"><info><title>Control Statements</title></info>
            

            <section xml:id="coding-standard.coding-style.control-statements.if-else-elseif"><info><title>If/Else/Elseif</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Control statements based on the <emphasis>if</emphasis> and
                    <emphasis>elseif</emphasis> constructs must have a single space before the
                    opening parenthesis of the conditional and a single space after the closing
                    parenthesis.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Within the conditional statements between the parentheses, operators must be
                    separated by spaces for readability. Inner parentheses are encouraged to improve
                    logical grouping for larger conditional expressions.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The opening brace is written on the same line as the conditional statement. The
                    closing brace is always written on its own line. Any content within the braces
                    must be indented using four spaces.
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
if ($a != 2) {
    $a = 2;
}
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    If the conditional statement causes the line length to exceed the <link linkend="coding-standard.php-file-formatting.max-line-length">maximum line
                        length</link> and has several clauses, you may break the conditional into
                    multiple lines. In such a case, break the line prior to a logic operator, and
                    pad the line such that it aligns under the first character of the conditional
                    clause. The closing paren in the conditional will then be placed on a line with
                    the opening brace, with one space separating the two, at an indentation level
                    equivalent to the opening control statement.
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
if (($a == $b)
    && ($b == $c)
    || (Foo::CONST == $d)
) {
    $a = $d;
}
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    The intention of this latter declaration format is to prevent issues when
                    adding or removing clauses from the conditional during later revisions.
                </para>

                <para>
                    For "if" statements that include "elseif" or "else", the formatting conventions
                    are similar to the "if" construct. The following examples demonstrate proper
                    formatting for "if" statements with "else" and/or "elseif" constructs:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
if ($a != 2) {
    $a = 2;
} else {
    $a = 7;
}

if ($a != 2) {
    $a = 2;
} elseif ($a == 3) {
    $a = 4;
} else {
    $a = 7;
}

if (($a == $b)
    && ($b == $c)
    || (Foo::CONST == $d)
) {
    $a = $d;
} elseif (($a != $b)
          || ($b != $c)
) {
    $a = $c;
} else {
    $a = $b;
}
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    <acronym>PHP</acronym> allows statements to be written without braces in some
                    circumstances. This coding standard makes no differentiation- all "if",
                    "elseif" or "else" statements must use braces.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standards.coding-style.control-statements.switch"><info><title>Switch</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Control statements written with the "switch" statement must have a single space
                    before the opening parenthesis of the conditional statement and after the
                    closing parenthesis.
                </para>

                <para>
                    All content within the "switch" statement must be indented using four spaces.
                    Content under each "case" statement must be indented using an additional four
                    spaces.
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
switch ($numPeople) {
    case 1:
        break;

    case 2:
        break;

    default:
        break;
}
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    The construct <property>default</property> should never be omitted from a
                    <property>switch</property> statement.
                </para>

                <note>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Note</emphasis>: It is sometimes useful to write a
                        <property>case</property> statement which falls through to the next case by
                        not including a <property>break</property> or <property>return</property>
                        within that case. To distinguish these cases from bugs, any
                        <property>case</property> statement where <property>break</property> or
                        <property>return</property> are omitted should contain a comment indicating
                        that the break was intentionally omitted.
                    </para>
                </note>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="coding-standards.inline-documentation"><info><title>Inline Documentation</title></info>
            

            <section xml:id="coding-standards.inline-documentation.documentation-format"><info><title>Documentation Format</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    All documentation blocks ("docblocks") must be compatible with the phpDocumentor
                    format. Describing the phpDocumentor format is beyond the scope of this
                    document. For more information, visit: <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://phpdoc.org/">http://phpdoc.org/</link>
                </para>

                <para>
                    All class files must contain a "file-level" docblock at the top of each file and
                    a "class-level" docblock immediately above each class. Examples of such
                    docblocks can be found below.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standards.inline-documentation.files"><info><title>Files</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Every file that contains <acronym>PHP</acronym> code must have a docblock at
                    the top of the file that contains these phpDocumentor tags at a minimum:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
/**
 * Short description for file
 *
 * Long description for file (if any)...
 *
 * LICENSE: Some license information
 *
 * @category   Zend
 * @package    Zend_Magic
 * @subpackage Wand
 * @copyright  Copyright (c) 2005-2011 Zend Technologies USA Inc. (http://www.zend.com)
 * @license    http://framework.zend.com/license   BSD License
 * @link       http://framework.zend.com/package/PackageName
 * @since      File available since Release 1.5.0
*/
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    The <property>@category</property> annotation must have a value of "Zend".
                </para>

                <para>
                    The <property>@package</property> annotation must be assigned, and should be
                    equivalent to the component name of the class contained in the file; typically,
                    this will only have two segments, the "Zend" prefix, and the component name.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The <property>@subpackage</property> annotation is optional. If provided, it
                    should be the subcomponent name, minus the class prefix. In the example above,
                    the assumption is that the class in the file is either
                    "<classname>Zend_Magic_Wand</classname>", or uses that classname as part of its
                    prefix.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standards.inline-documentation.classes"><info><title>Classes</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Every class must have a docblock that contains these phpDocumentor tags at a
                    minimum:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
/**
 * Short description for class
 *
 * Long description for class (if any)...
 *
 * @category   Zend
 * @package    Zend_Magic
 * @subpackage Wand
 * @copyright  Copyright (c) 2005-2011 Zend Technologies USA Inc. (http://www.zend.com)
 * @license    http://framework.zend.com/license   BSD License
 * @version    Release: @package_version@
 * @link       http://framework.zend.com/package/PackageName
 * @since      Class available since Release 1.5.0
 * @deprecated Class deprecated in Release 2.0.0
 */
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    The <property>@category</property> annotation must have a value of "Zend".
                </para>

                <para>
                    The <property>@package</property> annotation must be assigned, and should be
                    equivalent to the component to which the class belongs; typically, this will
                    only have two segments, the "Zend" prefix, and the component name.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The <property>@subpackage</property> annotation is optional. If provided, it
                    should be the subcomponent name, minus the class prefix. In the example above,
                    the assumption is that the class described is either
                    "<classname>Zend_Magic_Wand</classname>", or uses that classname as part of its
                    prefix.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="coding-standards.inline-documentation.functions"><info><title>Functions</title></info>
                

                <para>
                    Every function, including object methods, must have a docblock that contains at
                    a minimum:
                </para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para>A description of the function</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>All of the arguments</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>All of the possible return values</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <para>
                    It is not necessary to use the "@access" tag because the access level is already
                    known from the "public", "private", or "protected" modifier used to declare the
                    function.
                </para>

                <para>
                    If a function or method may throw an exception, use @throws for all known
                    exception classes:
                </para>

                <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
@throws exceptionclass [description]
]]></programlisting>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>

</appendix>
