<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="introduction.installation"><info><title> Instalación</title></info>

    

    <para> Véase el apéndice <link linkend="requirements"> requisitos</link> para una lista
        detallada de requisitos para Zend Framework. </para>

    <para> La instalación del Zend Framework es muy simple. Una vez que haya descargado y
        descomprimido el framework, deberá añadir la carpeta <filename>/library</filename> de la
        distribución al principio de su "include path". También puede mover la carpeta "library" a
        cualquier otra posición (compartida o no) de su sistema de archivos. </para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://framework.zend.com/download">Descargar la última versión
                    estable.</link> Esta versión esta disponible en formatos
                    <filename>.zip</filename> . <filename>.tar.gz</filename> , es una buena opción
                para aquellos que comienzan o son nuevos en Zend Framework. </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://framework.zend.com/download/snapshot">Download the latest nightly
                    snapshot.</link> For those who would brave the cutting edge, the nightly
                snapshots represent the latest progress of Zend Framework development. Snapshots are
                bundled with documentation either in English only or in all available languages. If
                you anticipate working with the latest Zend Framework developments, consider using a
                Subversion ( <acronym>SVN</acronym> ) client. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para> Using a <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://subversion.tigris.org">Subversion</link> (
                    <acronym>SVN</acronym> ) client. Zend Framework is open source software, and the
                Subversion repository used for its development is publicly available. Consider using
                    <acronym>SVN</acronym> to get Zend Framework if you already use
                    <acronym>SVN</acronym> for your application development, want to contribute back
                to the framework, or need to upgrade your framework version more often than releases
                occur. </para>
            <para>
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.export.html">
                    Exporting</link> is useful if you want to get a particular framework revision
                without the <filename>.svn</filename> directories as created in a working copy. </para>
            <para>
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.checkout.html">
                    Check out a working copy</link> if you want contribute to Zend Framework, a
                working copy can be updated any time with <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.update.html"> svn
                    update</link> and changes can be commited to our <acronym>SVN</acronym>
                repository with the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.commit.html"> svn
                    commit</link> command. </para>
            <para> An <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.advanced.externals.html">
                    externals definition</link> is quite convenient for developers already using
                    <acronym>SVN</acronym> to manage their application's working copies. </para>
            <para> The <acronym>URL</acronym> for the trunk of Zend Framework's
                    <acronym>SVN</acronym> repository is: <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/standard/trunk">
                    http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/standard/trunk</link>
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para> Una vez que tenga disponible una copia de Zend Framework, su aplicación necesita poder
        acceder a las clases del framework. Aunque hay <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.php.net/manual/en/configuration.changes.php"> diferentes maneras de
            lograr esto</link> , su <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.php.net/manual/en/ini.core.php#ini.include-path">
            <methodname>include_path</methodname>
        </link> de <acronym>PHP</acronym> necesita contener una ruta a la librería de Zend
        Framework. </para>

    <para> Zend provides a <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://framework.zend.com/docs/quickstart">QuickStart</link>
        to get you up and running as quickly as possible. This is an excellent way to begin learning
        about the framework with an emphasis on real world examples that you can built upon. </para>

    <para> Ya que los componentes de Zend Framework están débilmente conectados, tiene la opción de
        usar cualquier combinación de ellos en sus aplicaciones. Los siguientes capítulos presentan
        una referencia exhaustiva de Zend Framework, componente a componente. </para>

</chapter>
