<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="zend.crypt.blockcipher"><title>Encrypt/decrypt using block ciphers</title>
    

    <para>
        <classname>Zend\Crypt\BlockCipher</classname> implements the encrypt-then-authenticate mode using <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMAC">HMAC</link> to provide authentication.
    </para>

    <para>
        The symmetric cipher can be choose with a specific adapter that implements the <classname>Zend\Crypt\Symmetric\SymmetricInterface</classname>.
        We support the standard algorithms of the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://php.net/manual/en/book.mcrypt.php">Mcrypt</link> extension. The adapter that implements the Mcrypt is <classname>Zend\Crypt\Symmetric\Mcrypt</classname>.
    </para>

    <para>
        In the following code we reported an example on how to use the BlockCipher class to encrypt-then-authenticate
        a string using the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Encryption_Standard">AES</link> block cipher (with a key of 256 bit) and the HMAC algorithm (using the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SHA-2">SHA-256</link> hash function).
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
use Zend\Crypt\BlockCipher;

$blockCipher = BlockCipher::factory('mcrypt', array('algo' => 'aes'));
$blockCipher->setKey('encryption key');
$result = $blockCipher->encrypt('this is a secret message');
echo "Encrypted text: $result \n";
]]></programlisting>

    <para>
        The BlockCipher is initialized using a factory method with the name of the cipher adapter to use (mcrypt)
        and the parameters to pass to the adapter (the AES algorithm). In order to encrypt a string we need to specify an
        encryption key and we used the <methodname>setKey()</methodname> method for that scope. The encryption is provided by the <methodname>encrypt()</methodname> method.
    </para>

    <para>
        The output of the encryption is a string, encoded in Base64 (default), that contains the HMAC value, the IV vector, and
        the encrypted text. The encryption mode used is the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Block_cipher_modes_of_operation#Cipher-block_chaining_.28CBC.29">CBC</link>
        (default with random <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Initialization_vector">IV</link>) and the hash algorithm of HMAC is SHA256 (default).
        The Mcrypt adapter encrypts using the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Padding_%28cryptography%29">PKCS#7 padding</link> mechanism by default. You can specify a different padding technique
        using a special adapter for that (Zend\Crypt\Symmetric\Padding). The encryption key and the authentication key for HMAC are
        generated using the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PBKDF2">PBKDF2</link> algorithm as key derivation function.
    </para>

    <note>
        <title>Key size</title>

        <para>
            The BlockCipher class uses always the longest size of the key, for a particular cipher.
            For instance, for the AES algorithm it uses 256 bits and for the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blowfish_%28cipher%29">Blowfish</link> algorithm it uses 448 bits.
        </para>
    </note>

    <para>
        You can change all the default settings passing the values to the factory parameters.
        For instance, if you want to use the Blowfish algorithm, with the CFB mode and the SHA512 hash function for HMAC you have to initialize the class as follow:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
use Zend\Crypt\BlockCipher;

$blockCipher = BlockCipher::factory('mcrypt', array(
                                'algo' => 'blowfish',
                                'mode' => 'cfb',
                                'hash' => 'sha512'
                            ));
]]></programlisting>

    <note>
        <title>Recommendation</title>

        <para>
            If you are not familiar with symmetric encryption techniques we strongly suggest to use the default values of the <classname>BlockCipher</classname> class.
            The default values are: AES algorithm, CBC mode, HMAC with SHA256, PKCS#7 padding.
        </para>
    </note>

    <para>
        To decrypt a string we can use the <methodname>decrypt()</methodname> method. In order to successfully decrypt a string we have to
        configure the BlockCipher with the same parameters of the encryption. In the previous example that means to
        reuse the AES algorithm with the same encryption key.
    </para>

    <para>
        We can also initialize the BlockCipher manually without use the factory method. We can inject the symmetric cipher adapter
        directly to the constructor of the BlockCipher class. For instance, we can rewrite the previous example as follow:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
use Zend\Crypt\BlockCipher;
use Zend\Crypt\Symmetric\Mcrypt;

$blockCipher = new BlockCipher(new Mcrypt(array('algo' => 'aes'));
$blockCipher->setKey('encryption key');
$result = $blockCipher->encrypt('this is a secret message');
echo "Encrypted text: $result \n";
]]></programlisting>

</section>
