<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<sect1 id="zend.feed.pubsubhubbub.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
        <classname>Zend_Feed_Pubsubhubbub</classname> is an implementation of the PubSubHubbub Core
        0.2 Specification (Working Draft). It offers implementations of a Pubsubhubbub Publisher and
        Subscriber suited to Zend Framework and other PHP applications.
    </para>

    <sect2>
        <title>What is Pubsubhubbub?</title>

        <para>
            Pubsubhubbub is an open, simple web-scale pubsub protocol. A common use case to enable
            blogs (Publishers) to "push" updates from their RSS or Atom feeds (Topics) to end
            Subscribers. These Subscribers will have subscribed to the blog's RSS or Atom feed via a
            Hub, a central server which is notified of any updates by the Publisher and which then
            distributes these updates to all Subscribers. Any feed may advertise that it supports
            one or more Hubs using an Atom namespaced link element with a rel attribute of "hub".
        </para>

        <para>
            Pubsubhubbub has garnered attention because it is a pubsub protocol which is easy to
            implement and which operates over HTTP. Its philosophy is to replace the traditional
            model where blog feeds have been polled at regular intervals to detect and retrieve
            updates.  Depending on the frequency of polling, this can take a lot of time to
            propagate updates to interested parties from planet aggregators to desktop readers. With
            a pubsub system in place, updates are not simply polled by Subscribers, they are pushed to
            Subscribers, elimenating any delay. For this reason, Pubsubhubbub forms part of what has
            been dubbed the real-time web.
        </para>

        <para>
            The protocol does not exist in isolation. Pubsub systems have been around for a while,
            such as the familiar Jabber Publish-Subscribe protocol, XEP-0060, or the less well known
            rssCloud (described in 2001).  However these have not achieved widespread adoption typically
            due to either their complexity, poor timing or lack of suitability for web applications.
            rssCloud, which was recently revived as a response to the appearance of Pubsubhubbub, has
            also seen its usage increase significantly though it lacks a formal specification and
            currently does not support Atom 1.0 feeds.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Perhaps surprisingly given its relative early age, Pubsubhubbub is already in use including
            in Google Reader, Feedburner, and there are plugins available for Wordpress blogs.
        </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
        <title>Zend_Feed_Pubsubhubbub</title>

        <para>
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Pubsubhubbub</classname> implements two sides of the Pubsubhubbub
            0.2 Specification: a Publisher and a Subscriber. It does not currently implement a Hub
            Server though this is in progress for a future Zend Framework release.
        </para>

        <para>
            A Publisher is responsible for notifying all supported Hubs (many can be supported to
            add redundancy to the system) of any updates to its feeds, whether they be Atom or RSS
            based. This is achieved by pinging the supported Hub Servers with the URL of the updated
            feed. In Pubsubhubbub terminology, any updatable resource capable of being subscribed
            to is referred to as a Topic. Once a ping is received, the Hub will request the updated
            feed, process it for updated items, and forward all updates to all Subscribers
            subscribed to that feed.
        </para>

        <para>
            A Subscriber is any party or application which subscribes to one or more Hubs to receive
            updates from a Topic hosted by a Publisher. The Subscriber never directly communicates
            with the Publisher since the Hub acts as an intermediary, accepting subscriptions and
            sending updates to subscribed Subscribers. The Subscriber therefore communicates only
            with the Hub, either to subscribe/unsubscribe to Topics, or when it receives updates
            from the Hub. This communication design ("Fat Pings") effectively removes the possibility of
            a "Thundering Herd" issue. This occurs in a pubsub system where the Hub merely informs
            Subscribers that an update is available, prompting all Subscribers to immediately retrieve
            the feed from the Publisher giving rise to a traffic spike. In Pubsubhubbub, the Hub
            distributes the actual update in a "Fat Ping" so the Publisher is not subjected to any
            traffic spike.
        </para>

        <para>
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Pubsubhubbub</classname> implements Pubsubhubbub Publishers and
            Subscribers with the
            classes <classname>Zend_Feed_Pubsubhubbub_Publisher</classname> and
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Pubsubhubbub_Subscriber</classname>. In addition, the Subscriber
            implementation may handle any feed updates forwarded from a Hub by using
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Pubsubhubbub_Subscriber_Callback</classname>.  These classes, their
            use cases, and APIs are covered in subsequent sections.
        </para>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
