<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<section
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xml:id="zend.form.intro">
    <title>Introduction to Zend\Form</title>

    <para>
        <classname>Zend\Form</classname> is intended primarily as a bridge between your domain
        models and the View Layer. It composes a thin layer of objects representing form elements,
        an <link linkend="zend.input-filter">InputFilter</link>, and a small number of methods for
        binding data to and from the form and attached objects.
    </para>

    <para>
        The component consists of:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <classname>Elements</classname>, which simply consist of a name and attributes.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <classname>Fieldsets</classname>, which extend from <classname>Elements</classname>,
                but allow composing other fieldsets and elements.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <classname>Forms</classname>, which extend from <classname>Fieldsets</classname>
                (and thus <classname>Elements</classname>), provide data and object binding, and
                compose <classname>InputFilters</classname>. Data binding is done via <classname
                    linkend="zend.stdlib.hydrator">Zend\Stdlib\Hydrator</classname>.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        To facilitate usage with the view layer, the <classname>Zend\Form</classname> component also
        aggregates a number of form-specific view helpers. These accept elements, fieldsets, and/or
        forms, and use the attributes they compose to render markup.
    </para>

    <para>
        A small number of specialized elements are provided for accomplishing application-centric
        tasks. These include the <classname>Csrf</classname> element, used to prevent Cross Site
        Request Forgery attacks, and the <classname>Captcha</classname> element, used to display and
        validate <link linkend="zend.captcha">CAPTCHAs</link>.
    </para>

    <para>
        A <classname>Factory</classname> is provided to facilitate creation of elements,
        fieldsets, forms, and the related input filter. The default <classname>Form</classname>
        implementation is backed by a factory to facilitate extension and ease the process of form
        creation.
    </para>

    <para>
        The code related to forms can often spread between a variety of concerns: a form definition,
        an input filter definition, a domain model class, and one or more hydrator implementations.
        As such, finding the various bits of code and how they relate can become tedious. To
        simplify the situation, you can also annotate your domain model class, detailing the various
        input filter definitions, attributes, and hydrators that should all be used together.
        <classname>Zend\Form\Annotation\AnnotationBuilder</classname> can then be used to build the
        various objects you need.
    </para>
</section>
