<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<sect1 id="zend.feed.writer">
    <title>Zend_Feed_Writer</title>

    <sect2 id="zend.feed.writer.introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Writer</classname> is the sibling component to
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Reader</classname> responsible for generating feeds for output. It
            supports the Atom 1.0 specification (RFC 4287) and RSS 2.0 as specified by the RSS
            Advisory Board (RSS 2.0.11). It does not deviate from these standards. It does, however,
            offer a simple Extension system which allows for any extension/module for either of
            these two specifications to be implemented if they are not provided out of the box.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            In many ways, <classname>Zend_Feed_Writer</classname> is the inverse of
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Reader</classname>. Where <classname>Zend_Feed_Reader</classname>
            focused on providing an easy to use architecture fronted by getter methods,
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Writer</classname> is fronted by similarly named setters or
            mutators. This ensures the API won't pose a learning curve to anyone familiar with
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Reader</classname>.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            As a result of this design, the rest may even be obvious. Behind the scenes, data set on
            any <classname>Zend_Feed_Reader</classname> object is translated at render time onto a
            <classname>DOMDocument</classname> object using the necessary feed elements. For each
            supported feed type there is both an Atom 1.0 and RSS 2.0 renderer. Using a
            <classname>DOMDocument</classname> rather a templating solution has numerous advantages,
            the most obvious being the ability to export the <classname>DOMDocument</classname> for
            additional processing and relying on PHP DOM for correct and valid rendering.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            As with <classname>Zend_Feed_Reader</classname>, <classname>Zend_Feed_Writer</classname>
            is a standalone replacement for <classname>Zend_Feed</classname>'s Builder architecture
            and is not compatible with those classes.
        </para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="zend.feed.writer.architecture">
        <title>Architecture</title>
        
        <para>
            The architecture of <classname>Zend_Feed_Writer</classname> is very simple. It has two
            core sets of classes: containers and renderers.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The containers include the <classname>Zend_Feed_Writer_Feed</classname> and
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Writer_Entry</classname> classes. The Entry classes can be attached
            to any Feed class. The sole purpose of these containers is to collect data about the
            feed to generate using a simple interface of setter methods. These methods perform some
            data validity testing. For example, it will validate any passed URIs, dates, etc. These
            checks are not tied to any of the feed standards. The container objects also contain
            methods to allow for fast rendering and export of the final feed, and these can be
            reused at will.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            While there are two data containers, there are four renderers - two matching container
            renderers per support feed type. The renderer accept a container, and based on its
            content attempt to generate a valid feed. If the renderer is unable to generate a valid
            feed, perhaps due to the container missing an obligatory data point, it will report this
            by throwing an <classname>Exception</classname>. While it is possible to ignore
            <classname>Exception</classname>s, this removes the default safeguard of ensuring you
            have sufficient data set to render a wholly valid feed.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Due to the system being divided between data containers and renderers, it can make
            Extensions somewhat interesting. A typical Extension offering namespaced feed and entry
            level elements, must itself reflect the exact same architecture, i.e. offer feed and
            entry level data containers, and matching renderers. There is, fortunately, no complex
            integration work required since all Extension classes are simply registered and
            automatically used by the core classes. We'll meet Extensions in more detail at the end
            of this section.
        </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="zend.feed.writer.getting.started">
        <title>Getting Started</title>
    
        <para>
            Using <classname>Zend_Feed_Reader</classname> is as simple as setting data and
            triggering the renderer. Here is an example to generate a minimal Atom 1.0 feed.
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
/**
 * Create the parent feed
 */
$feed = new Zend_Feed_Writer_Feed;
$feed->setTitle('Paddy\'s Blog');
$feed->setLink('http://www.example.com');
$feed->setFeedLink('http://www.example.com/atom', 'atom');
$feed->addAuthor(array(
    'name'  => 'Paddy',
    'email' => 'paddy@example.com',
    'uri'   => 'http://www.example.com',
));
$feed->setDateModified(time());
$feed->addHub('http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/');

/**
 * Add one or more entries. Note that entries must
 * be manually added once created.
 */
$entry = $feed->createEntry();
$entry->setTitle('All Your Base Are Belong To Us');
$entry->setLink('http://www.example.com/all-your-base-are-belong-to-us');
$entry->addAuthor(array(
    'name'  => 'Paddy',
    'email' => 'paddy@example.com',
    'uri'   => 'http://www.example.com',
));
$entry->setDateModified(time());
$entry->setDateCreated(time());
$entry->setDescription('Exposing the difficultly of porting games to English.');
$entry->setContent('I am not writing the article. The example is long enough as is ;).');
$feed->addEntry($entry);

/**
 * Render the resulting feed to Atom 1.0 and assign to $out.
 * You can substitute "atom" with "rss" to generate an RSS 2.0 feed.
 */
$out = $feed->export('atom');
]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The output rendered should be as follows:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="xml">
&#60;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&#62;
&#60;feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"&#62;
    &#60;title type="text"&#62;Paddy's Blog&#60;/title&#62;
    &#60;subtitle type="text"&#62;Writing about PC Games since 176 BC.&#60;/subtitle&#62;
    &#60;updated&#62;2009-12-14T20:28:18+00:00&#60;/updated&#62;
    &#60;generator uri="http://framework.zend.com" version="1.10.0alpha"&#62;
        Zend_Feed_Writer
    &#60;/generator&#62;
    &#60;link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.example.com"/&#62;
    &#60;link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.example.com/atom"/&#62;
    &#60;id&#62;http://www.example.com&#60;/id&#62;
    &#60;author&#62;
        &#60;name&#62;Paddy&#60;/name&#62;
        &#60;email&#62;paddy@example.com&#60;/email&#62;
        &#60;uri&#62;http://www.example.com&#60;/uri&#62;
    &#60;/author&#62;
    &#60;link rel="hub" href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/"/&#62;
    &#60;entry&#62;
        &#60;title type="html"&#62;&#60;![CDATA[All Your Base Are Belong To Us]]&#62;&#60;/title&#62;
        &#60;summary type="html"&#62;
            &#60;![CDATA[Exposing the difficultly of porting games to English.]]&#62;
        &#60;/summary&#62;
        &#60;published&#62;2009-12-14T20:28:18+00:00&#60;/published&#62;
        &#60;updated&#62;2009-12-14T20:28:18+00:00&#60;/updated&#62;
        &#60;link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.example.com/all-your-base-are-belong-to-us"/&#62;
        &#60;id&#62;http://www.example.com/all-your-base-are-belong-to-us&#60;/id&#62;
        &#60;author&#62;
        &#60;name&#62;Paddy&#60;/name&#62;
        &#60;email&#62;paddy@example.com&#60;/email&#62;
        &#60;uri&#62;http://www.example.com&#60;/uri&#62;
        &#60;/author&#62;
        &#60;content type="html"&#62;
            &#60;![CDATA[I am not writing the article. The example is long enough as is ;).]]&#62;
        &#60;/content&#62;
    &#60;/entry&#62;
&#60;/feed&#62;
</programlisting>

        <para>
            This is a perfect Atom 1.0 example. It should be noted that omitting an obligatory point
            of data, such as a title, will trigger an <classname>Exception</classname> when
            rendering as Atom 1.0. This will differ for RSS 2.0 since a title may be omitted so long
            as a description is present. This gives rise to Exceptions that differ between the two
            standards depending on the renderer in use. By design,
            <classname>Zend_Feed_Writer</classname> will not render an invalid feed for either
            standard unless the end-user deliberately elects to ignore all Exceptions.
        </para>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
