<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<sect1 id="zend.currency.options">
    <title>Options for currencies</title>

    <para>
        Depending on your needs, several options can be specified at instantiation. All of this
        options have default values. But sometimes it is necessary to define how your currencies
        will be rendered. This includes for example:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Currency symbol, shortname or name</emphasis>:
            </para>

            <para>
                <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> knows all currency names, abbreviations and
                signs. But sometimes you could be in need to define the string which has to be
                displayed as replacement for a currency.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Currency position</emphasis>:
            </para>

            <para>
                The position of the currency symbol is automatically defined. But sometimes you
                could be in need to define it manually.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Script</emphasis>:
            </para>

            <para>
                You could define the script which shall be used to display digits. Detailed
                information about scripts and their usage can be found in
                <classname>Zend_Locale</classname>'s chapter <link
                    linkend="zend.locale.numbersystems">Numeral System Conversion</link>.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Number formatting</emphasis>:
            </para>

            <para>
                The amount of currency (generally known as money value) is formatted by
                using the formatting rules defined by the locale. For example is the ','
                sign in English used as separator for thousands, but in German as precision
                sign.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        The following list mentions all options which could be set. They can either be set at
        initiation or by using the <methodname>setFormat()</methodname> method. In any case
        you have to give this options as array.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>currency</property></emphasis>: Defines the abbreviation
                which can be displayed.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>display</property></emphasis>: Defines which part of the
                currency should be used for displaying the currency representation. There are 4
                representations which can be used and which are all described in <link
                    linkend="zend.currency.description">this
                    table</link>.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>format</property></emphasis>: Defines the format which
                should be used for displaying numbers. This number-format includes for example
                the thousand separator. You can either use a default format by giving a locale
                identifier, or define the number-format manually. If no format is set the locale
                from the <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> object will be used. See <link
                    linkend="zend.locale.number.localize.table-1">the chapter about number
                    formatting</link> for details.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>locale</property></emphasis>: Defines a locale for this
                currency. It will be used for detecting the default values when other settings
                are omitted. Note that when you don't set a locale yourself, it will be detected
                automatically which could lead to problems.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>name</property></emphasis>: Defines the full currency name
                which can be displayed.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>position</property></emphasis>: Defines the position at
                which the currency description should be displayed. The supported positions are
                described <link
                    linkend="zend.currency.position">this section</link>.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>precision</property></emphasis>: Defines the precision which
                should be used for the currency representation. The default value depends on the
                locale and is for most locales <emphasis>2</emphasis>.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>script</property></emphasis>: Defined which script should
                be used for displaying digits. The default script for most locales is
                <emphasis>'Latn'</emphasis>, which includes the digits 0 to 9. Other
                scripts such as 'Arab' (Arabian) are using other digits. See <link
                    linkend="zend.locale.numbersystems">the chapter about numbering
                    systems</link> for details and available options.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>service</property></emphasis>: Defines the exchange service
                which has to be used when calculating with different currencies.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>symbol</property></emphasis>: Defines the currency symbol
                which can be displayed.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis><property>value</property></emphasis>: Defines the currency amount
                (money value). Using this option you should also set the
                <property>service</property> option.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        As you can see there is much which could be changed. Still as already mentioned the
        default values for this settings conform the official standard for currency
        representation in every country.
    </para>
</sect1>
