<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<sect2 id="zend.log.writers.zendmonitor">
    <title>Writing to the Zend Server Monitor</title>

    <para>
        <classname>Zend_Log_Writer_ZendMonitor</classname> allows you to log events via Zend
        Server's Monitor API. This allows you to aggregate log messages for your entire application
        environment in a single location. Internally, it simply uses the
        <functionname>monitor_custom_event()</functionname> function from the Zend Monitor API.
    </para>

    <para>
        One particularly useful feature of the Monitor API is that it allows you to specify
        arbitrary custom information alongside the log message. For instance, if you wish to log an
        exception, you can log not just the exception message, but pass the entire exception object
        to the function, and then inspect the object within the Zend Server event monitor.
    </para>

    <note>
        <title>Zend Monitor must be installed and enabled</title>

        <para>
            In order to use this log writer, Zend Monitor must be both installed and enabled.
            However, it is designed such that if Zend Monitor is not detected, it will simply act as
            a null logger.
        </para>
    </note>

    <para>
        Instantiating the <classname>ZendMonitor</classname> log writer is trivial:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$writer = new Zend_Log_Writer_ZendMonitor();
$log    = new Zend_Log($writer);
]]></programlisting>

    <para>
        Then, simply log messages as usual:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$log->info('This is a message');
]]></programlisting>

    <para>
        If you want to specify additional information to log with the event, pass that information
        in a second parameter:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$log->info('Exception occurred', $e);
]]></programlisting>

    <para>
        The second parameter may be a scalar, object, or array; if you need to pass multiple pieces
        of information, the best way to do so is to pass an associative array.
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$log->info('Exception occurred', array(
    'request'   => $request,
    'exception' => $e,
));
]]></programlisting>

    <para>
        Within Zend Server, your event is logged as a "custom event". From the "Monitor" tab, select
        the "Events" sub-item, and then filter on "Custom" to see custom events.
    </para>

    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/zend.log.writers.zendmonitor-events.png"
                format="PNG"></imagedata>

            <caption>
                <para>
                    Events in Zend Server's Monitor dashboard
                </para>
            </caption>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>
        In this screenshot, the first two events listed are custom events logged via the
        <classname>ZendMonitor</classname> log writer. You may then click on an event to view all
        information related to it.
    </para>

    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/zend.log.writers.zendmonitor-event.png"
                format="PNG"></imagedata>

            <caption>
                <para>
                    Event detail in Zend Server's Monitor
                </para>
            </caption>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>
        Clicking on the "Custom" sub tab will detail any extra information you logged by passing the
        second argument to the logging method. This information will be logged as the
        <varname>info</varname> subkey; you can see that the request object was logged in this
        example.
    </para>

    <note>
        <title>Integration with Zend_Application</title>

        <para>
            The <classname>ZendMonitor</classname> log writer has a corresponding <link
                linkend="zend.application.available-resources.zendmonitor"><classname>Zend_Application</classname>
                bootstrap resource</link>. If you create your
            project using the <command>zf.sh</command> or <command>zf.bat</command> command, this
            resource will be registered for you by default, and used in your
            <classname>ErrorController</classname> to log application exceptions.
        </para>
    </note>
</sect2>
