<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xml:id="zend.db.row-gateway">
    <title>Zend\Db\RowGateway</title>

    <para>
        <classname>Zend\Db\RowGateway</classname> is a sub-component of Zend\Db
        that implements the Row Gateway pattern from PoEAA.  This effectively
        means that Row Gateway objects primarily model a row in a database, and
        have methods such as save() and delete() that will help persist this
        row-as-an-object in the database itself.  Likewise, after a row from the
        database is retrieved, it can then be manipulated and save()'d back to
        the database in the same position (row), or it can be delete()'d from the
        table.
    </para>

    <para>
        The interface for a Row Gateway object simply adds save() and delete()
        and this is the interface that should be assumed when a component has a
        dependency that is expected to be an instance of a RowGateway object:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
interface RowGatewayInterface
{
    public function save();
    public function delete();
}
]]></programlisting>

    <section xml:id="zend.db.row-gateway.row-gateway">
        <title>Quickstart</title>

        <para>
            While most of the time, RowGateway will be used in conjucntion with
            other Zend\Db\ResultSet producing objects, it is possible to use it
            standalone.  To use it standalone, you simply need an Adapter and a
            set of data to work with.  The following use case demonstrates
            Zend\Db\RowGateway\RowGateway usage in its simplest form:
        </para>

        <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
use Zend\Db\RowGateway\RowGateway;

// naturally, you'd use parameterization where possible and proper quoting
$resultSet = $adapter->query('SELECT * FROM "user" WHERE "id" = 2');

// get array of data
$rowData = $resultSet->current()->toArray();

// row gateway
$rowGateway = new RowGateway('id', 'my_table', $adapter);
$rowGateway->populate($rowData);

$rowGateway->first_name = 'New Name';
$rowGateway->save();

// or delete this row:
$rowGateway->delete();
]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The workflow described above is greatly simplified when RowGateway
            is used in conjunction with the TableGateway feature.  What this
            achieves is a Table Gateway object that when select()'ing from a
            table, will produce a ResultSet that is then capable of producing
            valid Row Gateway objects.  Its usage looks like this:
        </para>

        <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
use Zend\Db\TableGateway;
use Zend\Db\TableGateway\Feature;

$table = new TableGateway('artist', $adapter, new Feature\RowGatewayFeature('id'));
$results = $table->select(array('id' => 2));

$artistRow = $results->current(); // Zend\Db\RowGateway\RowGateway
$artistRow->name = 'New Name';
$artistRow->save();
]]></programlisting>



    </section>

</section>
