<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="zend.crypt.key.derivation"><title>Key derivation function</title>
    

    <para>
        In cryptography, a key derivation function (or KDF) derives one or more secret keys from a secret value such as a master key
        or other known information such as a password or passphrase using a pseudo-random function.
        For instance, a KDF function can be used to generate encryption or authentication keys from a user password.
        The <classname>Zend\Crypt\Key\Derivation</classname> implements a key derivation function using specific adapters.
    </para>

    <para>
        The adapter implemented so far is the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PBKDF2">PBKDF2</link> algorithm. In the example below we show how to use it:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
use Zend\Crypt\Key\Derivation\PBKDF2;
use Zend\Math\Math;

$pass = 'password';
$salt = Math::randBytes(strlen($pass), true);
$key  = PBKDF2::calc('sha256', $pass, $salt, 10000, strlen($pass)*2);

echo "Original password: $pass \n";
echo "Key derivation   : $key \n";
]]></programlisting>

    <para>
        In this example the PBKDF2 algorithm takes the password ($pass) and generate a binary key with a size double of the password.
        The syntax of PBKDF2 is <methodname>calc($hash, $pass, $salt, $iterations, $length)</methodname> where $hash is the name of the hash
        function to use, $pass is the password, $salt is a pseudo random value, $iterations is the number of iterations of the algorithm and $length
        is the size of the key to be generated.
        We used the <methodname>randBytes()</methodname> function of the <classname>Zend\Math\Math</classname> class to generate a random bytes using strong generators (the true options means the usage of strong generators).
    </para>

    <para>
        The number of iterations is a very important parameter for the security of the algorithm. Big values means more security. There is not a fixed
        value for that because the number of iterations depends on the CPU power. You should choose a number of iteration that prevent brute force attacks.
        For instance, a value of 1'000'000 iterations, that is equal to 1 sec of elaboration for the PBKDF2 algorithm, is enough secure using an Intel Core i5-2500 CPU at 3.3 Ghz.
    </para>

</section>
