<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<sect1 id="zend.currency.usage">

    <title>How to Work with Currencies</title>

    <para>
        To use <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> within your application, create an instance of
        it without any parameters. This will create an instance of
        <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> with your locale set and defines the currency which
        should be used for this locale.
    </para>

    <example id="zend.currency.usage.example1">

        <title>Creating an Instance of Zend_Currency from the Locale</title>

        <para>
            Assume you have 'en_US' set as the set locale by the user or your environment. By
            passing no parameters while creating the instance you tell
            <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> to use the currency from the locale 'en_US'. This
            leads to an instance with US Dollar set as the currency with formatting rules from
            'en_US'.
        </para>

        <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$currency = new Zend_Currency();
]]></programlisting>

    </example>

    <para>
        <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> also supports the usage of an application-wide locale.
        You can set a <classname>Zend_Locale</classname> instance in the registry as shown below.
        With this notation you can avoid setting the locale manually for each instance when you want
        to use the same locale throughout the application.
    </para>

    <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
// in your bootstrap file
$locale = new Zend_Locale('de_AT');
Zend_Registry::set('Zend_Locale', $locale);

// somewhere in your application
$currency = new Zend_Currency();
]]></programlisting>

    <note>
        <para>
            If your system has no default locale, or if the locale of your system can not be
            detected automatically, <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> will throw an exception. If
            see this exception, you should consider setting the locale manually.
        </para>
    </note>

    <para>
        Depending on your needs, several parameters can be specified at instantiation. Each of
        these parameters is optional and can be omitted. Even the order of the parameters can be
        switched. The meaning of each parameter is described in this list:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis>currency</emphasis>:
            </para>
            <para>
                A locale can include several currencies. Therefore the first parameter
                <emphasis>'currency'</emphasis> can define which currency should be used by giving
                the short name or full name of that currency. If that currency in not recognized in
                any locale an exception will be thrown. Currency short names are always made up of 3
                letters, written in uppercase. Well known currency shortnames include
                <acronym>USD</acronym> or <acronym>EUR</acronym>.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis>locale</emphasis>:
            </para>
            <para>
                The <emphasis>'locale'</emphasis> parameter defines which locale should be
                used for formatting the currency. The specified locale will also be used to get the
                script and symbol for this currency if these parameters are not given.
            </para>
            <note>
                <para>
                    Note that <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> only accepts locales which
                    include a region. This means that all locales that only include a language will
                    result in an exception. For example the locale <emphasis>en</emphasis> will
                    cause an exception to be thrown whereas the locale <emphasis>en_US</emphasis>
                    will return <acronym>USD</acronym> as currency.
                </para>
            </note>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <example id="zend.currency.usage.example2">

        <title>Other Ways to Create Instances of Zend_Currency</title>

        <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
// expect standard locale 'de_AT'

// creates an instance from 'en_US' using 'USD' which is default
// currency for 'en_US'
$currency = new Zend_Currency('en_US');

// creates an instance from the set locale ('de_AT') using 'EUR' as
// currency
$currency = new Zend_Currency();

// creates an instance using 'EUR' as currency, 'en_US' for number
// formating
$currency = new Zend_Currency('en_US', 'EUR');
]]></programlisting>

    </example>

    <para>
        You can omit any of the parameters to <classname>Zend_Currency</classname>'s constructor if
        you want to use the default values. This has no negative effect on handling the currencies.
        It can be useful if, for example, you don't know the default currency for a region.
    </para>

    <note>
        <para>
            For many countries there are several known currencies. Typically, one currency will
            currently be in use, with one or more ancient currencies. If the
            '<emphasis>currency</emphasis>' parameter is suppressed the contemporary currency will
            be used. The region '<emphasis>de</emphasis>' for example knows the currencies
            '<acronym>EUR</acronym>' and '<acronym>DEM</acronym>'... '<acronym>EUR</acronym>'
            is the contemporary currency and will be used if the currency parameter is omitted.
        </para>
    </note>

    <sect2 id="zend.currency.usage.tocurrency">

        <title>Creating and Output String from a Currency</title>

        <para>
            To get a numeric value converted to an output string formatted for the currency at hand,
            use the method <methodname>toCurrency()</methodname>. It takes the value which should be
            converted. The value itself can be any normalized number.
        </para>

        <para>
            If you have a localized number you will have to convert it first to an normalized number
            with <link
                linkend="zend.locale.number.normalize">Zend_Locale_Format::getNumber()</link>. It
            may then be used with <methodname>toCurrency()</methodname> to create a currency output
            string.
        </para>

        <para>
            <methodname>toCurrency(array $options)</methodname> accepts an array with options which
            can be used to temporarily set another format or currency representation. For details
            about which options can be used see <link
                linkend="zend.currency.usage.setformat">Changing the Format of a Currency</link>.
        </para>

        <example id="zend.currency.usage.tocurrency.example">

            <title>Creating an Output String for a Currency</title>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
// creates an instance with 'en_US' using 'USD', which is the default
// values for 'en_US'
$currency = new Zend_Currency('en_US');

// prints '$ 1,000.00'
echo $currency->toCurrency(1000);

// prints '$ 1.000,00'
echo $currency->toCurrency(1000, array('format' => 'de_AT'));

// prints '$ ١٬٠٠٠٫٠٠'
echo $currency->toCurrency(1000, array('script' => 'Arab'));
]]></programlisting>

        </example>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.currency.usage.setformat">

        <title>Changing the Format of a Currency</title>

        <para>
            The format which is used by creation of a <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> instance
            is, of course, the standard format. But occasionally it is necessary to change this
            format.
        </para>

        <para>
            The format of an currency output includes the following parts:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Currency symbol, shortname or name</emphasis>:
                </para>
                <para>
                    The symbol of the currency is normally displayed within the currency output
                    string. It can be suppressed when needed or even overwritten.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Currency position</emphasis>:
                </para>
                <para>
                    The position of the currency symbol is normally automatically defined by the
                    locale. It can be changed if necessary.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Script</emphasis>:
                </para>
                <para>
                    The script which shall be used to display digits. Detailed information about
                    scripts and their usage can be found in the documentation of
                    <classname>Zend_Locale</classname> in the chapter <link
                        linkend="zend.locale.numbersystems">Numeral System Conversion</link>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Number formatting</emphasis>:
                </para>
                <para>
                    The amount of currency (formally known as value of money) is formatted by the
                    usage of formatting rules within the locale. For example is in English the ','
                    sign used as separator for thousands, and in German the '.' sign.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            So if you need to change the format, you should the <methodname>setFormat()</methodname>
            method. It takes an array which should include every option you want to change. The
            <varname>$options</varname> array supports the following settings:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>position</emphasis>: Defines the position at which the currency
                    description should be displayed. The supported positions can be found in <link
                        linkend="zend.currency.usage.setformat.constantsposition">this table</link>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>script</emphasis>: Defined which script should be used for
                    displaying digits. The default script for most locales is
                    <emphasis>'Latn'</emphasis>, which includes the digits 0 to 9. Other
                    scripts such as 'Arab' (Arabian) can be used.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>format</emphasis>: Defines the format which should be used for
                    displaying numbers. This number-format includes for example the thousand
                    separator. You can either use a default format by giving a locale identifier,
                    or define the number-format manually. If no format is set the locale from the
                    <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> object will be used.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>display</emphasis>: Defines which part of the currency should be
                    used for displaying the currency representation. There are 4 representations
                    which can be used and which are all described in <link
                        linkend="zend.currency.usage.setformat.constantsdescription">this
                        table</link>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>precision</emphasis>: Defines the precision which should be used for
                    the currency representation. The default value is <emphasis>2</emphasis>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>name</emphasis>: Defines the full currency name which should be
                    displayed. This option overwrites any currency name which is set through
                    the creation of <classname>Zend_Currency</classname>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>currency</emphasis>: Defines the international abbreviation which
                    should be displayed. This option overwrites any abbreviation which is set
                    through the creation of <classname>Zend_Currency</classname>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>symbol</emphasis>: Defines the currency symbol which should be
                    displayed. This option overwrites any symbol which is set through
                    the creation of <classname>Zend_Currency</classname>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <table id="zend.currency.usage.setformat.constantsdescription">

            <title>Constants for the selecting the currency description</title>

            <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>constant</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><constant>NO_SYMBOL</constant></entry>
                        <entry>Do not display any currency representation</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><constant>USE_SYMBOL</constant></entry>
                        <entry>Display the currency symbol</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><constant>USE_SHORTNAME</constant></entry>
                        <entry>Display the 3 lettered international currency abbreviation</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><constant>USE_NAME</constant></entry>
                        <entry>Display the full currency name</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>

        </table>

        <table id="zend.currency.usage.setformat.constantsposition">

            <title>Constants for the selecting the position of the currency description</title>

            <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>constant</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><constant>STANDARD</constant></entry>
                        <entry>Set the standard position as defined within the locale</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><constant>RIGHT</constant></entry>
                        <entry>
                            Display the currency representation at the right side of the value
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><constant>LEFT</constant></entry>
                        <entry>
                            Display the currency representation at the left side of the value
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>

        </table>

        <example id="zend.currency.usage.setformat.example">

            <title>Changing the displayed format of a currency</title>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
// creates an instance with 'en_US' using 'USD', 'Latin' and 'en_US' as
// these are the default values from 'en_US'
$currency = new Zend_Currency('en_US');

// prints 'US$ 1,000.00'
echo $currency->toCurrency(1000);

$currency->setFormat(array('display' => Zend_Currency::USE_NAME,
                           'position' => Zend_Currency::RIGHT));

// prints '1.000,00 US Dollar'
echo $currency->toCurrency(1000);

$currency->setFormat(array('name' => 'American Dollar'));
// prints '1.000,00 American Dollar'
echo $currency->toCurrency(1000);

$currency->setFormat(array('format' => '##0.00'));
// prints '1000,00 American Dollar'
echo $currency->toCurrency(1000);
]]></programlisting>

        </example>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.currency.usage.informational">

        <title>Reference Methods for Zend_Currency</title>

        <para>
            Of course, <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> supports also methods to get information
            about any existing and many ancient currencies from <classname>Zend_Locale</classname>.
            The supported methods are:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis><methodname>getSymbol()</methodname></emphasis>:
                </para>
                <para>
                    Returns the known symbol of the set currency or a given currency. For example
                    <emphasis>$</emphasis> for the US Dollar within the locale
                    '<emphasis>en_US</emphasis>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis><methodname>getShortName()</methodname></emphasis>:
                </para>
                <para>
                    Returns the abbreviation of the set currency or a given currency. For example
                    <acronym>USD</acronym> for the US Dollar within the locale
                    '<emphasis>en_US</emphasis>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis><methodname>getName()</methodname></emphasis>:
                </para>
                <para>
                    Returns the full name of the set currency of a given currency. For example
                    <emphasis>US Dollar</emphasis> for the US Dollar within the locale
                    '<emphasis>en_US</emphasis>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis><methodname>getRegionList()</methodname></emphasis>:
                </para>
                <para>
                    Returns a list of regions where the set currency or a given one is known to be
                    used. It is possible that a currency is used within several regions, so the
                    return value is always an array.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis><methodname>getCurrencyList()</methodname></emphasis>:
                </para>
                <para>
                    Returns a list of currencies which are used in the given region.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            The function <methodname>getSymbol()</methodname>,
            <methodname>getShortName()</methodname> and <methodname>getName()</methodname> accept
            two optional parameters. If no parameter is given the
            expected data will be returned from the set currency. The first parameter takes the
            shortname of a currency. Short names are always three lettered, for example
            <acronym>EUR</acronym> for euro or <acronym>USD</acronym> for US Dollar. The second
            parameter defines from which locale the data should be read. If no locale is given, the
            set locale is used.
        </para>

        <example id="zend.currency.usage.informational.example">

            <title>Getting Information about Currencies</title>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
// creates an instance with 'en_US' using 'USD', 'Latin' and 'en_US'
// as these are the default values from 'en_US'
$currency = new Zend_Currency('en_US');

// prints '$'
echo $currency->getSymbol();

// prints 'EUR'
echo $currency->getShortName('EUR');

// prints 'Österreichische Schilling'
echo $currency->getName('ATS', 'de_AT');

// returns an array with all regions where USD is used
print_r($currency->getRegionList();

// returns an array with all currencies which were ever used in this
// region
print_r($currency->getCurrencyList('de_AT');
]]></programlisting>

        </example>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.currency.usage.setlocale">

        <title>Settings new default values</title>

        <para>
            The method <methodname>setLocale()</methodname> allows to set a new locale for
            <classname>Zend_Currency</classname>. All default values for the currency will be
            overwritten when this method is invoked. This includes currency name, abbreviation and
            symbol.
        </para>

        <example id="zend.currency.usage.setlocale.example">

            <title>Setting a New Locale</title>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
// get the currency for US
$currency = new Zend_Currency('en_US');
print $currency->toCurrency(1000);

// get the currency for AT
$currency->setLocale('de_AT');
print $currency->toCurrency(1000);
]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.currency.usage.cache">

        <title>Zend_Currency Performance Optimization</title>

        <para>
            <classname>Zend_Currency</classname>'s performance can be optimized using
            <classname>Zend_Cache</classname>. The static method
            <methodname>Zend_Currency::setCache($cache)</methodname> accepts one option: a
            <classname>Zend_Cache</classname> adapter. If the cache adapter is set, the localization
            data that <classname>Zend_Currency</classname> uses are cached. There are some static
            methods for manipulating the cache: <methodname>getCache()</methodname>,
            <methodname>hasCache()</methodname>, <methodname>clearCache()</methodname> and
            <methodname>removeCache()</methodname>.
        </para>

        <example id="zend.currency.usage.cache.example">

            <title>Caching currencies</title>

            <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
// creating a cache object
$cache = Zend_Cache::factory('Core',
                             'File',
                             array('lifetime' => 120,
                                   'automatic_serialization' => true),
                             array('cache_dir'
                                       => dirname(__FILE__) . '/_files/'));
Zend_Currency::setCache($cache);
]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

</sect1>
