<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Reviewed: no -->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="zend.http.overview">
    <info><title>Zend\Http</title></info>

    <section xml:id="zend.http.overview.intro">
        <info><title>Overview</title></info>
        
        <para>
            <classname>Zend\Http</classname> is a primary foundational component of Zend Framework.
            Since much of what PHP does is web-based, specifically HTTP, it makes sense to have a
            performant, extensible, concise and consistent API to do all things HTTP.  In nutshell,
            there are several parts of <classname>Zend\Http:</classname>
        </para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Context-less <classname>Request</classname> and <classname>Response</classname>
                    classes that expose a fluent API for introspecting several aspects of HTTP
                    messages:
                </para>
                
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Request line information and response status information
                        </para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Parameters, such as those found in <acronym>POST</acronym> and
                            <acronym>GET</acronym>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Message Body</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Headers</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    A Client implementation with various adapters that allow for sending requests
                    and introspecting responses.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="zend.http.overview.request-response-and-headers">
        <info><title>Zend\Http Request, Response and Headers</title></info>
    
        <para>
            The Request, Response and Headers portion of the <classname>Zend\Http</classname>
            component provides a fluent, object-oriented interface for introspecting information
            from all the various parts of an HTTP request or HTTP response.  The two main objects
            are <classname>Zend\Http\Request</classname> and
            <classname>Zend\Http\Response</classname>.  These two classes are "context-less",
            meaning that they model a request or response in the same way whether it is presented by
            a client (to <emphasis>send</emphasis> a request and <emphasis>receive</emphasis> a
            response) or by a server (to <emphasis>receive</emphasis> a request and
            <emphasis>send</emphasis> a response).  In other words, regardless of the context, the
            API remains the same for introspecting their various respective parts. Each attempts to
            fully model a request or response so that a developer can create these objects from a
            factory, or create and populate them manually.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
