<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="zend.json.advanced"><info><title>Advanced Usage of Zend_Json</title></info>
    

    <section xml:id="zend.json.advanced.objects1"><info><title>JSON Objects</title></info>
        

        <para>
            When encoding <acronym>PHP</acronym> objects as <acronym>JSON</acronym>, all public
            properties of that object will be encoded in a <acronym>JSON</acronym> object.
        </para>

        <para>
            <acronym>JSON</acronym> does not allow object references, so care should be taken not to
            encode objects with recursive references. If you have issues with
            recursion, <methodname>Zend_Json::encode()</methodname> and
            <methodname>Zend_Json_Encoder::encode()</methodname> allow an optional second
            parameter to check for recursion; if an object is serialized twice, an
            exception will be thrown.
        </para>

        <para>
            Decoding <acronym>JSON</acronym> objects poses an additional difficulty, however, since
            Javascript objects correspond most closely to <acronym>PHP</acronym>'s associative
            array. Some suggest that a class identifier should be passed, and an object
            instance of that class should be created and populated with the
            key/value pairs of the <acronym>JSON</acronym> object; others feel this could pose a
            substantial security risk.
        </para>

        <para>
            By default, <classname>Zend_Json</classname> will decode <acronym>JSON</acronym> objects
            as associative arrays. However, if you desire an object returned, you can specify this:
        </para>

        <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
// Decode JSON objects as PHP objects
$phpNative = Zend_Json::decode($encodedValue, Zend_Json::TYPE_OBJECT);
]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Any objects thus decoded are returned as <classname>StdClass</classname> objects
            with properties corresponding to the key/value pairs in the <acronym>JSON</acronym>
            notation.
        </para>

        <para>
            The recommendation of Zend Framework is that the individual
            developer should decide how to decode <acronym>JSON</acronym> objects. If an object of a
            specified type should be created, it can be created in the developer
            code and populated with the values decoded using <classname>Zend_Json</classname>.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="zend.json.advanced.objects2"><info><title>Encoding PHP objects</title></info>
        

        <para>
            If you are encoding <acronym>PHP</acronym> objects by default the encoding mechanism
            can only access public properties of these objects. When a method
            <methodname>toJson()</methodname> is implemented on an object to encode,
            <classname>Zend_Json</classname> calls this method and expects the object to return a
            <acronym>JSON</acronym> representation of its internal state.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="zend.json.advanced.internal"><info><title>Internal Encoder/Decoder</title></info>
        

        <para>
            <classname>Zend_Json</classname> has two different modes depending if ext/json is
            enabled in your <acronym>PHP</acronym> installation or not. If ext/json is installed by
            default <methodname>json_encode()</methodname> and
            <methodname>json_decode()</methodname> functions are used for encoding and decoding
            <acronym>JSON</acronym>. If ext/json is not installed a Zend Framework implementation in
            <acronym>PHP</acronym> code is used for en-/decoding. This is considerably slower than
            using the <acronym>PHP</acronym> extension, but behaves exactly the same.
        </para>

        <para>
            Still sometimes you might want to use the internal encoder/decoder even
            if you have ext/json installed. You can achieve this by calling:
        </para>

        <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
Zend_Json::$useBuiltinEncoderDecoder = true:
]]></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="zend.json.advanced.expr"><info><title>JSON Expressions</title></info>
        

        <para>
            Javascript makes heavy use of anonymnous function callbacks, which can be saved
            within <acronym>JSON</acronym> object variables. Still they only work if not
            returned inside double qoutes, which <classname>Zend_Json</classname> naturally does.
            With the Expression support for <classname>Zend_Json</classname> support you can encode
            <acronym>JSON</acronym> objects with valid javascript callbacks. This works for both
            <methodname>json_encode()</methodname> or the internal encoder.
        </para>

        <para>
            A javascript callback is represented using the <classname>Zend_Json_Expr</classname>
            object. It implements the value object pattern and is immutable. You can set the
            javascript expression as the first constructor argument. By default
            <classname>Zend_Json::encode</classname> does not encode javascript callbacks, you have
            to pass the option <property>enableJsonExprFinder</property> and set it to
            <constant>TRUE</constant> into the <methodname>encode</methodname> function. If
            enabled the expression support works for all nested expressions in large object
            structures. A usage example would look like:
        </para>

        <programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[
$data = array(
    'onClick' => new Zend_Json_Expr('function() {'
              . 'alert("I am a valid javascript callback '
              . 'created by Zend_Json"); }'),
    'other' => 'no expression',
);
$jsonObjectWithExpression = Zend_Json::encode(
    $data,
    false,
    array('enableJsonExprFinder' => true)
);
]]></programlisting>
    </section>
</section>
